He is hungry.
It's fast and weighs almost a ton,
(music)
but it is not the only giant predator at the shark center.
More large shark species live here than anywhere else on the planet.
(music)
They all share a current.
A vital sigh that joins a perfect shark storm.
Shark Rules.
The great white shark is the largest cold water predator, but also a world traveler,
and this male is about to begin an epic journey.
He is ready to leave when a sudden current of cold water diverts his course to a place
distant hunting.
Clouds of crustaceans accumulate in cold places.
He needs food before he leaves, but crustaceans are not in his diet.
Chase a trail.
Something in the distance.
Something that is at the other end of the food chain.
The enormous humpback whales.
(music)
Whales gather to eat the crustaceans brought by the current.
The biggest ones eat the small ones,
(music)
but this shark has an insatiable appetite
and giants are not invincible.
This is what the great white shark perceives.
Even dead, the whale moves with the current.
The smell of rotting fat that it gives off is like a drug to the great white shark.
(music)
Before a long journey, a great white shark must sate itself with food.
He needs all the energy he can get for the journey ahead.
(music)
Despite its size, you must be alert to danger.
There will always be someone bigger
and this species has not survived 11 million years because it is naive.
(music)
The dead whale is a good farewell gift before the journey.
And it's designed to eat this.
It has triangular teeth in a springy jaw made for holding and slicing.
He can't bite for long.
You need to move to breathe,
but the more he eats, the greater his appetite.
(music)
The great white shark is famous for its binge eating.
If there is food, he takes it.
(music)
The pieces of fat are converted into energy that is stored in your large liver.
His movements are almost...
mechanics.
(music)
His stomach is full of fat, the fuel that will take him to a distant shore called
shark center.
It's a 1,400-kilometer journey from where you are at the tip of Africa,
where two streams meet: one cold and rich with nutrients,
and the other warm and comforting.
Once a year, the cold current reaches the coast and a countercurrent is created.
The great white shark will travel on it to a unique meeting
where an incredible mix of sea hunters awaits.
He knows exactly where he's going and will need to feed himself along the way.
The next stop is the kelp beds.
There is plenty of prey here.
Young sea lions are snacks for a shark.
His island castle has a seaweed moat.
A security fence included that for a sea lion it is...
like a playground.
(music)
New puppies are arriving right now.
All of them beautiful, tender and defenseless,
But for a great white shark they are delicious little bites.
Maybe they are safe on the island,
But there is something that the white shark knows very well,
the coast is certain death.
If any little one wants to feed, he will have to leave the fortress.
sooner or later.
Leaving the island and the seaweed is not safe, but the seals must hunt far out to sea.
And waiting just at the edge of the deep waters is the great white shark.
The seals walk in groups at first, but eventually each one goes on its own.
Seals are fast, but they're no match for a flying shark.
It took them by surprise,
awesome.
At first it stays down,
crawling deep,
look up
and chases the silhouettes.
Incredibly, great white sharks can generate body heat.
Even in icy waters, their engines are warm
and ready to unleash extraordinary energy in a single burst.
A special vein supplies the shark's brain with warm blood,
So he's not just fast, he thinks fast.
Relative to their size, sharks have some of the largest livers on the planet.
and they not only serve as fuel containers, but they also give them dynamism
and its high fat content gives them strength when they need it most.
I can see you, but do you see me?
(music)
The timing must be perfect.
Seals are fast.
(music)
The prey has half the chance of escaping.
This one was lucky.
The next one maybe not so much.
It's time to leave them alone.
The journey awaits and the current presses.
Ahead, the flow is heading towards the coast,
where it collides with the warm current of the Indian Ocean.
The shark station is up ahead.
The current changes rhythm and begins to churn, mixing cold water with warm water.
Every eddy and pulse drives the feast toward the shore, uniting species from temperate waters
and tropical.
The current extends about 160 kilometers.
A place with a shark population like almost no other.
Cold water fish gather in the current, safe and slippery
and migrate to the tropics to spawn.
Tons of food on the move.
The current hypnotizes them.
This is why the great white shark is here
(music)
and even seals follow him.
These clouds of fish are the big attraction.
More great white sharks bring up the rear, but other species await ahead.
A mix of predators moves in to corner the fish
and collides with the newly arrived sharks.
Bull sharks, sand sharks and several of these.
The black tips.
This day hunter is aerodynamic and fast
and grows up to 2.5 meters.
A giant, if you're a 4-inch mackerel.
Blacktips travel with the current and approach the coast,
preparing to enjoy the feast that awaits there.
They have little hope.
Sharks surround the giant ball of prey.
Blacktips hunt along the banks, forcing small fish to congregate.
A blacktip swishes its tail to reach speeds of up to 22 kilometers per hour.
Its snout opens almost 90 degrees.
A big breath.
(music)
At first the group is large,
then it decreases
(music)
more and more
until it disappears.
The environment is left clean.
Now the current crashes against the coast and heads towards the shark farm.
Just 4 meters from the coast the waters reach a huge reef system
plagued by other giants.
(music)
It is a junction of currents, one day warm, the next cold.
A melting pot of sharks.
(music)
There are more species here than anywhere else on the planet.
It is the kingdom of elasmobranchs, fish with cartilaginous skeletons,
sharks, rays and the like.
(music)
During the day it is a beautiful aquarium,
but the darkness reveals an underworld and a timid giant.
One by one they emerge from the caves and grottos.
Bull sharks are on the prowl.
There may be thousands of sharks here, but bull sharks dominate the reef niches.
At almost twice the length of a man, this is a gathering of giants.
Unlike blacktips and whitetips,
Bulls do not need to swim to breathe.
They pump water into their gills as they stalk.
They appear lethargic, but can be extremely fast.
While great white sharks cut with their teeth, bull sharks tear and rip with theirs,
and are eager to use them.
The bull shark has some secrets.
This is a couples date night.
The scars prove it.
The female shows teeth marks from the males who held her.
But mating whets the appetite.
Its needle-like teeth do not slice, but pierce.
His eyes are tiny, so he uses his electromagnetic sense
to find food.
The black spots on its head are gel sacs that detect vibrations from other fish.
If your heart beats, there is no escape.
Flatfish like sole are practically invisible,
but she is an expert at finding them.
(music)
It's not just sharks that the current brings with it.
This old male sea turtle is also an ocean traveler.
He swam south from tropical waters and is exhausted from all the mating.
His work is done, but he needs to regain his energy soon.
Its shell is its only protection and for most predators
It is impenetrable, but a majority does not mean "all."
A tiger shark.
If the great white shark is the giant of the south, he is the giant of the north.
It is twice as long as a king-size bed,
(music)
and he is a hunter, a scavenger, and a garbage container.
Tigers have one of the most acidic stomachs in the animal kingdom.
From beer bottles to explosives, they are known for eating everything.
He is also traveling.
Tiger sharks can travel 1,100 kilometers in a month.
This one travels from the tropical waters of the south...
to hunt.
(music)
His navigation skills are impeccable.
Get to know this reef.
He comes here every year...
for food.
It is no coincidence that the turtle is the most sought after, alive or dead.
(music)
The exhausted sea turtle comes up for air,
but it stays up longer than it should.
The old turtle served his kind well
and is now part of the cycle of life.
(music)
The jaws of the tiger are wide and short
and combined with a powerful jaw can easily pierce through bone.
And divides the portions of his food precisely.
(music)
The 220-kilogram turtle looks like a rag doll.
under the awesome power of the shark.
(music)
Its unique teeth work like a heavy-duty can opener.
and the shark extracts the proteins from inside.
(music)
Tiger sharks are truly successful predators.
At the end of its hunting trip, the shark returns north.
You must reach the tropics, where the water is warm and comforting.
That's where it will reproduce in spring, where the backwash dissipates.
While cruising through the shark farm, you pass someone else's hatchery.
The mouth of the river.
Fresh water flows into the ocean, warming the current.
This special mix of fresh and salt water is a nursery for millions of fish,
although just upstream lurks a real river monster.
Rarely seen, but one of the most dangerous sharks in the world.
The sardine shark.
This is where he spends a lot of time, close to humans.
It is the only shark adapted to survive in fresh water indefinitely.
This female swims upriver to mate.
Despite the murky color of the mud-laden water,
will give birth to her young kilometers upriver in this estuary.
Bull sharks can spend months in freshwater systems.
and have been found more than 3 thousand kilometers in the river.
Here you will live with the people, for whom, without knowing it,
making your daily routine potentially life-threatening.
The excellent hearing and sense of smell of the bull shark
compensate for the reduced vision in such dirty waters.
She is an expert hunter in the river and also in the ocean.
Bull sharks are famous for their short, blunt snouts and aggressive nature.
They are excellent predators in the open sea.
The diminished current leads them to the northern limits of the shark center.
The great sharks of the tropics converge here.
Blacktips are also hunting here.
The great masses of dams are a distant memory.
As spring approaches, they look for an opportunity,
or take advantage of other people's waste.
This is also the territory of silvertip sharks.
and hammerhead sharks.
Silvertips are aggressive and territorial.
They try to dominate anyone else of the same size.
Hammers play a secondary role here.
It's the neighborhood of the silvertips and they will never stray far,
but all will retreat before the powerful Sardinian.
Large schools of fish patrol the shark center.
They are vicious predators, but bull sharks lurk from below.
If anyone swims alone in the current, they will be a target.
(music)
One big bite and it will be your fi.
The other sharks are hungry too.
And here's another victim.
The bull shark's skeleton may be elastic, but its jaws are as hard as rock.
They have the most powerful bite of all sharks.
Sarda sharks are not the largest sharks the current offers.
The waters are electric blue.
There are plenty of palm trees.
Welcome to the tropics.
Here, an inlet of warm water dissipates the cold water,
but what it brings goes much further.
If crustaceans are the driving force of the cold south,
Here, the abundance of shrimp colors the waters pink.
They don't look like that many up close, but there are billions of them.
To eat them all at once there is only one strategy.
Being super giant.
As big as a school bus.
A 12-meter whale shark.
And there are many of them.
They are some of the largest fish on the planet
and yet they feed on the smallest creatures in the sea.
And it is difficult for him to be satisfied.
Whale sharks have more than 3,000 small teeth, but they don't bite.
They use the powerful muscles in their throats to suck in tons of shrimp.
with jaws almost 2 meters wide.
The water then gushes out through the gills.
Anything larger than a match head is trapped in special sponges.
which he then swallows.
(music)
This makes whale sharks one of the world's largest water filterers.
More than 5 thousand liters of water pass through its mouth every hour
and catch about 32 thousand shrimp in the process.
(music)
He is tireless,
going forward and sucking in vast portions of ocean.
(music)
For him, the lottery does not exist.
It depends on the large volumes.
(music)
It may seem strange for a fish of its size to feed on something so small,
But consuming small prey in abundance makes sense in terms of energy.
(music)
By doing this, you consume more than 30 million calories a day.
Schools of mackerel follow them.
(music)
They know that whale sharks will always find food.
The last fruits of the wealth of the stream are exhausted.
(music)
All the big sharks that were attracted
Now they will move away to meet again next year.
(music)